(
"ai_sub_version": "1.11.0",
"subtitles_prompt_version": 3,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": "gemini-cli:gemini-3-flash-preview",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true
),
"gemini_cli": (
"timeout": 600
)
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": true,
"fps": 1,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"encoder": "libx264"
)
),
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"subtitles": 8
),
"retry": (
"run": 3,
"max": 9,
"delay": 30
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false
)
MUST RE:LIVE
ホロライブ公式スタンプ「獅白ぼたん」 全24種
Hololive Official Stamps "Shishiro Botan" - All 24 types
「だからあたしは世界を旅している。『オンガク』を見つけるために」
"That's why I'm traveling the world. To find 'music.'"
「そう、この世界線ではそうなのね」
"I see, so that's how it is in this timeline."
「だってうちは...... キミのことが大好きだから！」
"Because I... love you very much!"
「わたあめは 非常食、じゃないよ〜！」
"Wata-ame isn't emergency food~!"
「きみを見たとき、ビビビッてきたの！！」
"When I saw you, it felt like a spark!!"
「そういう時はね、ぱーっと麦ジュースを飲むに限るかな〜？」
"At times like that, maybe there's nothing better than downing some wheat juice~?"
「ねぇ、気になるなら 今からここで私といっしょにやってみる？ ──『ライブ』ってやつ」
"Hey, if you're curious, why don't you try it with me right now? This thing called a 'live.'"
「君が来るのを待ってたよ。この世界に......『オンガク』を取り戻すことができる君をね」
"I've been waiting for you to come. For you, who can bring 'music' back to this world."
世界がこんな風になって、どれくらい経っただろう
How much time has passed since the world became like this?
どこまでも続く荒野、木々や植物に侵食され崩れた建物、砂漠に埋もれ傾く巨大なビル群
An endless wasteland, buildings crumbling and overgrown with plants, and massive skyscrapers buried in the sand.
もうずっとずっと前に起きた災厄によって、世界は滅びてしまった
The world was destroyed by a catastrophe that occurred a long, long time ago.
そんな黄昏を迎えた世界で、あたしは失われた文明の遺物を探すことを生業としている
In this world at its twilight, I make a living searching for the relics of a lost civilization.
浄水器や濾過器のような今でも使えるものから、使い道のわからない箱のようなもの、朽ちかけた布などなど......
From things still useful like water purifiers and filters, to mysterious boxes, tattered cloth, and more...
そういったものを手に入れて、旅人として日々を過ごしながら、ずっと探しているものがある
While collecting such things and living as a traveler, there is something I have been searching for all along.
それは遥か昔にこの世界から失われてしまった……「オンガク」というもの
That is something lost from this world a long time ago... something called "music."
それが何かはわからない
I don't know what it is.
どうして探そうとしているのかも……よくはわからない
I don't really know why I'm trying to find it, either.
でも不思議とその響きに、惹かれるのだ
But for some reason, I'm drawn to that sound.
だからあたしは世界を旅している
That's why I'm traveling the world.
答えを探して、彷徨っている
Wandering in search of an answer.
「オンガク」を見つけるために
To find "music."
獅白ぼたん 「『オンガク』を見つけるために」
Shishiro Botan: "To find 'Music'"
さ、今日も頑張っていくかー
Well, shall I do my best today too?
いっせーの！
One, two, go!
儚い鼓動 おしまずに
Without sparing a single fleeting heartbeat
流れる時間を追い越して
Overtaking the flowing time
駆け抜ける世界
In this world we race through
幾つもの名前と
With so many different names
幾つもの姿を使い分けて
And so many different forms to alternate between
うまく生きているけれど
I'm living my life well enough, but...
胸の奥痛いよ
My chest aches deep inside
音立てて軋むよ
Creaking with a heavy sound
きっと心 命 ここにあるから
Because my heart and life are surely right here
EXCP (Exciter) 新しい明日へ
EXCP (Exciter) toward a new tomorrow
EXCP 今漕ぎ出す
EXCP setting sail right now
EXCP 運命の波間にさらわれたくはない
EXCP I don't want to be swept away by the waves of fate
いっせーの！
One, two, go!
儚い鼓動 おしまずに
Without sparing a single fleeting heartbeat
流れる時間を追い越して
Overtaking the flowing time
駆け抜ける世界
In this world we race through
I'm a Master 私はいつも祈ってる
I'm a Master, I'm always praying
熱い想いをぶつけたら
If I pour my burning feelings into it
奇跡さえ起こせるから
Because I can even make miracles happen
この景色すべては
This entire landscape
寂しさでできてる
Is made out of loneliness
願うだけですぐに そばにいられた
I could be by your side just by wishing for it
あの頃の姿を
Searching for that form
追い求めさまよう
Wandering as I seek it out
きっと火花 言葉 ここにあるから
Because the sparks and words are surely right here
EXCP 懐かしい歌声
EXCP a nostalgic singing voice
EXCP 今聞こえる
EXCP I can hear it now
EXCP 記憶の中でも受け取れるのはなぜ
EXCP why is it I can still receive it within my memories?
通じ合う その喜びを感じたい
I want to feel that joy of connecting with each other
場所も時間も飛び越えて
Leaping across space and time
分け合える世界
A world we can share
信じあう 音がすべてと悟ったよ
I've realized that the sound of mutual belief is everything
君をもう一度見つけたら
If I can find you once again
涙さえ輝くから
Even my tears will sparkle
I'm a Master...
いっせーの！
One, two, go!
儚い鼓動 おしまずに
Without sparing a single fleeting heartbeat
流れる時間を追い越して
Overtaking the flowing time
駆け抜ける世界
In this world we race through
通じ合う その喜びを感じたい
I want to feel that joy of connecting with each other
場所も時間も飛び越えて
Leaping across space and time
分け合える世界
A world we can share
信じあう 音がすべてと悟ったよ
I've realized that the sound of mutual belief is everything
君をもう一度見つけたら
If I can find you once again
涙さえ輝くから
Even my tears will sparkle
I'm a Master...
もうこの世界には、人はあまり残っていない
There aren't many people left in this world anymore.
文明が崩壊して、インフラもなにもかもなくなってしまったのだから、
Civilization has collapsed, and infrastructure and everything else is gone,
仕方ないことだと思う。
so I suppose it's only natural.
だけど旅をしていると、何かに引き寄せられるように誰かと出会うことがある
But when you're traveling, you sometimes encounter someone as if drawn by something.
旅をしていると、何かに引き寄せられるように誰かと出会うことがある。
When traveling, you sometimes meet someone as if drawn by something.
こんなふうに...
Like this...
こんにちは。
Hello.
こんにちは。あなたは？
Hello. And you are?
私はAZKi。この世界の地図を作りながら
I'm AZKi. While making a map of this world,
いろいろなところを調査する『開拓者』をしているわ。君は？
I work as a 'pioneer' investigating various places. And you?
あたしは旅をしてるんだ。
I'm traveling.
なくなってしまった大切なものを探すために。
To find something precious that was lost.
大切なもの？
Something precious?
うん……『オンガク』を。
Yes... 'Music'.
ふむ……そう、この世界線ではそうなのね。
Hmm... I see, that's how it is in this worldline.
でもあなたは覚えているはずだわ。
But you should remember it.
ん？
Hmm?
記憶にはなくても、胸の奥の深いところに、
Even if not in your memories, deep in your heart,
一緒に過ごした時間……気持ちを一つにした瞬間を。
the time we spent together... the moments our feelings became one.
だってあなたにとってそれは……とても大事なものだったはずだから。
Because for you, that... must have been something very important.
完全少女論
Kanjou Shoujoron (Full Theory of a Girl)
作詞・作曲：北澤伸一郎
Lyrics/Composition: Shinichiro Kitazawa
あー 君が好きな服
Ah, the clothes you like
濡れたままだね
Are still soaking wet
こんな夜だから
Because it's a night like this
響かせてミュージック
Let the music echo
お気に入りの歌は
Your favorite song
君は知らない
You don't know it
君だけ知らない
Only you don't know it
感情論を君に投げつけて
Throwing my emotional theories at you
傷ついたふりしてるけど
Pretending that I'm hurt
完全相違 いつも居たいくらい
Totally different, but I want to be here forever
もっと確かめてみる
I'll try to check even more
全然論外 だけど涙出る
Completely out of the question, but tears fall
見ないでよ ひどいかもなのお
Don't look at me, it might be awful
単純じゃんって 言われたくないよ
I don't want you to say it's simple
もっと確かめてみて
Try to check even more
ねえ 朝が来る前に
Hey, before morning comes
連れ出してみて
Try to take me out
こんな夜だから
Because it's a night like this
鳴り止まないミュージック
The music won't stop ringing
お気に入りの曲は
To your favorite track
君は踊らない
You don't dance
君だけ踊らない
Only you don't dance
感情論で君を傷つけて
Hurting you with emotional theories
こんなひと嫌いになるでしょ
You'll start to hate someone like this, right?
純情なんて 呆れるくらいに
Pure innocence, to an amazing degree
本当似合わないけど
Really doesn't suit me, but
テンションちょっと 上げて知らんぷり
Raising the tension a bit and playing dumb
困らせたい そんな気分よ
I want to trouble you, that's the mood
単純じゃんって 言われたくないよ
I don't want you to say it's simple
きっとわがままだけど
I'm sure I'm being selfish, but
完全少女論 自己中心度 気分上昇度 いいじゃんこれで
Theory of a Full Girl: Egotism, mood swings... isn't this fine?
不全純情度 未完成情緒 一言論外でしょ
Imperfect innocence, incomplete emotions... it's out of the question, right?
ほんのちょっと 手を伸ばして
Stretching out my hand just a little
きっと全然気づかない
You probably won't notice at all
笑うよ 朝が来たら
I'll laugh when morning comes
大丈夫
It's all right
だから 感情論を君に投げつけて
So, throwing my emotional theories at you
演じてるふりしてるけど
Pretending like I'm acting
完全相違 いつも居たいくらい
Totally different, but I want to be here forever
君は優しいけれど
Though you are kind
感情論を君に投げつけて
Throwing my emotional theories at you
傷ついたふりしてるけど
Pretending that I'm hurt
完全相違 いつも居たいくらい
Totally different, but I want to be here forever
もっと確かめてみる
I'll try to check even more
はぁ……
(Sigh)
さっきのは……なんだったんだろう
What was that just now...?
たくさんの人たちと、その人たちが発する熱気に包まれて、私はすごくワクワクしてた
Surrounded by so many people and the heat they emitted, I was really excited.
別だかすごく懐かしい感じがした……
It felt somehow very nostalgic...
ねえねえ、キミ、大丈夫？
Hey, hey, you okay?
え？
Eh?
なんか顔色が良くなかったからさ
You didn't look very well.
あ、うちはミオだよ。占い師をやってる
Oh, I'm Mio. I'm a fortune teller.
ん、キミ、何かを探してるね。そう占いにでてる
Hmm, you're looking for something. That's what the fortune says.
わかるの？
You can tell?
うん、よかったら話してみて、何か力になれるかもしれないし
Yeah, if you'd like, try talking to me. I might be able to help.
実は……
Actually...
なるほど……キミは『オンガク』を探してるんだね
I see... You're looking for "Music".
それならあそこに行ってみればいいんじゃない？
In that case, why don't you try going over there?
世界の果てにあるっていう、光の塔
The Tower of Light, which is said to be at the edge of the world.
そこには天使が住んでて、やってきた人の願いを叶えてくれるんだって
They say an angel lives there, and they grant the wishes of those who visit.
だからそこに行ってお願いをすれば、キミの探しものも見つかるんじゃないかな
So if you go there and make a wish, maybe you'll find what you're looking for.
親切にありがとう、そこに行ってみることにするよ！
Thank you for your kindness, I'll try going there!
どういたしまして。でもお礼なんていらないって
You're welcome. But I told you, you don't need to thank me.
ん？
Hm?
だってうちは……キミのことが大好きだから！
Because I... love you!
ずっとずっと前からね！
Since a long, long time ago!
コトダマ紡ぐ未来
作詞：石川泰 作曲：田辺トシノ
Kotodama Tsumugu Mirai
Lyrics: Yasushi Ishikawa Composition: Toshino Tanabe
遥か 遠く 続く
Far, far away, continuing...
果てなき道
...an endless road.
それでも いつか
Even so, someday...
辿り着くと信じて
...believing that I will arrive.
たとえ 今は
Even if now...
辛く 厳しくても
...is hard and painful.
小さな 笑顔 守る
Protecting a small smile...
全て捧げて
...giving everything.
心 重なる
Hearts overlapping...
言葉より強い絆に
...in a bond stronger than words.
染め上げていく
Dyeing it all...
ひとつになる鼓動で
...with a heartbeat that becomes one.
記憶辿る 追憶の旅 続けて
Tracing memories, continuing the journey of reminiscence.
あらゆることを 受け止めるから
Because I'll accept everything...
言葉はいらないの
...words are not needed.
それは 永遠に
That is eternally...
いつも 近く そばで
Always near, by your side...
見ていたけど
...I was watching.
気づかずに いても
Even if I didn't notice...
今は 遠く感じる
...now it feels far away.
あとを 追いかけ
Chasing after you...
絆から愛に変われば
...if the bond turns into love.
染め上げていく
Dyeing it all...
二人だけの秘密
...a secret just between the two of us.
想いを込めた 言葉の強さ 信じて
Believing in the strength of words filled with feelings.
…見てる
...Watching
うちに秘めたとき
When I kept it inside
覚悟していた
I was prepared
未来を紡ぐために
In order to spin the future
気が付けばほら
If you notice, look
心に宿る
It dwells in my heart
ともしび
A lamp
小さな光
A small light
寄り添い合えば
If we snuggle up together
そう　未来を指して
Yes, pointing to the future
青く広がる
Spreading blue
晴れ渡る空
A clear sky
見上げる
Looking up
もう言葉すら
Already, even words
いらないから
Aren't needed anymore
ただ　抱きしめていて
Just keep holding me
時は永遠に
Time is eternal
降り注ぐ雨のような歓声
(Cheers like pouring rain)
その中で、煌びやかな服を着たあたしは、幸せそうな笑顔で手を振っている
(In the midst of that, wearing glittering clothes, I wave with a happy smile)
（まるでもう一人のあたしのように）
(As if it were another me)
世界の果てにあるという光の塔
The Tower of Light, said to be at the edge of the world
『オンガク』を探すために、あたしはそこを目指すことに決めた
To find "Music," I decided to head there
何日かかるかわからないけど、幸いなことに時間はたくさんある
I don't know how many days it'll take, but fortunately, I have plenty of time
ただ……
Only...
お腹、空いた……
(Stomach growling) I'm hungry...
あ
Ah
なんでわためを見てお腹を鳴らしてるの！？
Why is your stomach growling while looking at Watame!?
え、わかんないけど、なんか君を見たら急に
Eh, I don't know, but looking at you just made me suddenly...
わためは『非常食』じゃないよ〜！
Watame isn't "emergency food"!
見逃してくれたら、代わりにわためが歌うから〜
If you let me go, Watame will sing for you instead!
……歌？
...Singing?
歌って……何？
Singing... what is that?
え、君、歌を知らないの？
Eh, you don't know about singing?
よーし、じゃあわためが教えてあげるよ。
Alright, then Watame will teach you.
歌っていうのはね……
Singing is, you see...
滅びてゆくこのステラ
This stella is perishing
絆を辿るストーリー
A story tracing bonds
受け継ぐ想いが
May the inherited feelings
生まれ変われますように
Be reborn
目の前 現れた無表情は
The expressionless face that appeared before me
誰にも懐を見せないまま
Without showing its heart to anyone
事象が世界を歪ませて
Events distort the world
光がただ眩しすぎた
The light was just too bright
燦々と照りつける
Shining brilliantly
荒野に残した足跡
Footprints left in the wasteland
与えられたのなら
If it was given to us
守るものだけ
Only things to protect
滅びてゆくこのステラ
This stella is perishing
叶うことがないとしても
Even if it never comes true
変えよう 世界を
Let's change the world
灯してゆく
Keeping it lit
震える手が弾いた
Trembling hands plucked
意味を持たない銃口
A meaningless muzzle
輝く星の下
Under the shining stars
私は今 息をする
I am breathing now
それなら あなたは騙したんだ
In that case, you deceived me
breath of stella
今なら
If it's now
全て分かってしまう
I'll understand everything
名前を
Your name...
呼んでくれていても
even if you're calling it
私に
to me...
届けられていなかった
it wasn't being delivered
消える日の前でただ
Just before the day it disappears
立ち尽くして煙る灰
standing still, smoking ash
命の理屈がいま
The logic of life now
答えをせまる
demands an answer
滅びてゆくその中で
Within that which is perishing
息を凝らした分くらい
about as much as I held my breath
解れた絆を
the unraveled bonds
振り解いて
shaking them off
お願いどうかそばにいて
Please, somehow stay by my side
声が銃声に求めた
My voice sought it in the gunshot
終わりと始まりの
Of the end and the beginning
時の中で
within the time
Ah...
瞳の奥に映った
Reflected in the depths of your eyes
壊れかけている
broken and crumbling
心に持つ
held in the heart
引き金に
on the trigger
かけた指
the finger placed
先が示す未来を
the future shown ahead
祈るだろう
I will pray for it
Ah...
滅びてゆくこのステラ
This Stella that is perishing
瞬きの数の傷
Scars numbering as many as blinks
心がこのまま
Even if my heart remains this way
途絶えてしまっても
and ceases to be
私の生まれた理由も
The reason I was born, too
手放さないでお願い
please don't let go of it
終わりと始まりの
Of the end and the beginning
時の中で
within the time
Ah...
私はここにいるよ
I am here
何度でも確かめられるよ
I can confirm it as many times as it takes
心の存在と名前を
The existence of the heart and my name
あなたが生き抜いた世界は
The world you lived through
まだ私の中で息をする
still breathes within me
光、光、光
Light, light, light
その星のような煌めきが――頭に焼き付いて離れない
That star-like shimmer—is burned into my mind and won't leave.
あの子がやっていたことは何なんだろう？
What was that girl doing?
「ウタ」にって言ってたけど……初めて聞く言葉だ
She said 'uta' (song)... it's the first time I've heard that word.
だけどウタは、あたしの心の深いところに確かに染み込んできた……
But the song certainly soaked into the deep parts of my heart...
静かだなぁ……
It's quiet...
この世界は、ずっと静寂に包まれている
This world has always been shrouded in silence.
だけどさっきのあれは――「ウタ」は、そのどれとも違った
But that thing just now—the 'song'—was different from any of that.
あれは、何なんだろう……
What was that...
あと別れ際にくれたこの頭につける道具は……？遺物……？
And this tool for my head she gave me as we parted...? An artifact...?
確か「ヘッドセット」って言ってた
I think she called it a 'headset'.
これを使えば……あたしも「歌」えるんだろうか
If I use this... I wonder if I can 'sing' too.
forever has gone,
today is infinity
and yesterday's dreams,
today a faint memory (Ah)
forever has gone,
today is infinity
it's time to move on,
forever has gone
Disintegration
作詞：Ben 作曲：高瀬一矢
Lyrics: Ben Composition: Kazuya Takase
two eyes in the face of billions of voices
I saw the flashing lights move further in the distance
(dream was not meant to be)
and outside these walls that I have created
the sound of stars colliding
echoes in the distance
and dreams they shatter
let it break into a thousand pieces
let the wind blow it all away
dreams are fragile but our hearts grow
stronger from the memories...
let it break into a thousand pieces
let the wind blow it all away
dreams are fragile but our hearts grow
stronger from the memories...
renew... the light...
the dream...
forever has gone,
today is infinity
and yesterday's dreams,
today a faint memory (Ah)
forever has gone,
today is infinity
it's time to move on,
(time to move on)
(it's time to move on,)
forever has gone
(time to move on)
(it's time to move)
It's time to move
and outside these walls that I have created
the sound of stars colliding
echoes in the distance
and dreams they shatter
let it break into a thousand pieces
let the wind blow it all away
dreams are fragile but our hearts grow
stronger from the memories...
let it break into a thousand pieces
let the wind blow it all away
dreams are fragile but our hearts grow
stronger from the memories...
renew... the light...
the dream...
forever has gone,
today is infinity
and yesterday's dreams,
today a faint memory (Ah)
forever has gone,
today is infinity
it's time to move on,
forever has gone
「ウタ」を知ってから、数日が経った。
A few days have passed since I learned about 'songs'.
旅路は進み、ようやく光の塔がおぼろげながらに見えてくる
My journey continues, and at last, the Tower of Light is coming into view, however faintly.
だけど「オンガク」や「ウタ」について知っている人は、ほとんどいなかった
But there were almost no people who knew about 'music' or 'songs'.
もしかしたらあたしは、ないものねだりをしているだけなのかもしれない
Maybe I'm just asking for the impossible.
でも……新しい出会いはあった
But... there was a new encounter.
Ciaooo! I'm Raora Panthera!
あたし、絵描きをやってるんだ！
I'm an artist!
きみをみたとき、ビビッてきたの！きみにはこれが似合いそう！
When I saw you, I felt a spark! This would look good on you!
さらさらさら……っと。 はい、プレゼント！
Scribble scribble... here, a present!
はい！プレゼント！
Here! A present!
これ…あたし？
Is this... me?
うん。
Yeah.
ステージ衣装を着た、君の絵！So cute……
A drawing of you in your stage outfit! So cute...
ちょ、ちょっとあたしには可愛すぎない？
W-Wait, isn't it a bit too cute for me?
そんなことないよー！
That's not true!
すっごくぴったり！
It suits you perfectly!
そ、そうかな…？
R-Really...?
きみは、この「ステージ衣装」を着て……
You'll wear this stage outfit...
Let's sing with me!
ILLEXECUTION
作詞：えびかれー伯爵 / 划代  作曲：えびかれー伯爵
Lyrics: Count Ebi-Curry / Kakushiro  Composition: Count Ebi-Curry
YEAH~
The knacks of surviving in this world
are being human and being right
Everyone keeps telling me to grow up fast
And it is so tough, can't wrap my head around it
Your unfair rules
Ego trip into a loop
We do belong nowhere in this world
Yet we are surviving
Getting through anything
Stay alive
Hated ones
Naked hearts
Worthless games that never end
Found them in the darkness in the end
何が正しくて
What is right,
何が間違っているんだ
and what is wrong?
僕はただ、
I just,
ここで生きてると
want to shout
叫びたいだけ
that I'm living here.
I heard voices calling out my true name
I will never give up
or be swayed anymore
Nobody can stop me
This is the way I am
I'll execute you, drop dead baby
YEAH~
Everyone wanna choose the right path only
They would seek salvation in this closed world
Filthy hands and mind never get clean again though
And it is so tough, can't wrap my head around it
Cannot turn the clock back
Cannot take a turn back
We do belong nowhere in this world
Yet we are surviving
Getting through anything
Stay alive
Missing piece
Warmth of hands
Joys and even stabbing pains
Found them in the darkness in the end
何が正しくて
What is right,
何が間違っているんだ
and what is wrong?
誰だって、
Everyone is,
ここで生きてると
shouting that
叫んでいるのに
they are living here.
Facing what they really want to do
They'll make it at the cost of everything
Nobody can stop me
This is the way I am
I'll execute you, drop dead baby
YEAH~
また失って、もう嫌になって
I lost it again, and I'm sick of it
それでも消えなくて
But it won't disappear
その心の名をなんと言うのだろう
What do you call the name of that heart?
僕はここで今、叫んでいるんだよ
I am here right now, shouting
君だって、ここで同じように
You, too, are in the same way here
叫んでいるんだろう
shouting, I suppose.
I heard voices calling out my true name
I will never give up
or be swayed anymore
Nobody can stop me
This is the way I am
I'll execute you, drop dead baby
YEAH~
So, this is the way I am
色とりどりのいかわいらしい「衣装」
Colorful and cute "outfits."
それは不思議とぴったりと身体に馴染んでいた
Strangely, they fit my body perfectly.
「衣装」を身にまとい、「ヘッドセット」をつけて、「歌う私」
Wearing the "outfit," the "headset," and "singing"...
あっちの私と、今の私。どっちが本物なんだろう
The me over there and the me now. Which one is real?
そういう時はね、難しいことを忘れてパーっと楽しいことをするに限るかな。
In times like that, it's best to forget the hard stuff and just have a blast doing fun things.
クレープを焼いたりとか、アロマで癒されたりとか、
Like making crepes, or relaxing with aromatherapy,
ベリーダンスを踊ったりとかして気持ちよくなれば、悩み事なんてどこかに飛んでいっちゃうものなんだよ。
or doing some belly dancing to feel good. Then your worries will just fly away.
そういうものなの？
Is that how it works?
うん、そういうものかな。
Yeah, I guess so.
だって世の中の大体のことは、それがどう見えるかっていうのは見る人次第なんだから。
After all, most things in this world depend on how the person seeing them perceives it.
例えばアキロゼのこの格好が芸術的に見えるかセクシーに見えるかはあなたたち次第、みたいにね。
For example, whether Akirose's outfit looks artistic or sexy... depends on all of you. See?
ふふ。
Hehe.
え、あ、うん。
Er, ah, yeah.
そうだ、せっかくこうして出会えたんだから、一緒に踊ろっか？
I know! Since we've finally met like this, shall we dance together?
あなたとアキロゼの二人で。
Just the two of us, you and Akirose.
え、でも私、踊ったことなんてないんだけど。
What? But I've never danced before.
大丈夫大丈夫。
It's okay, it's okay.
これはあなたのためだけに考えた、踊り子アキロゼの振り付けだから。
This choreography was created by dancer Akirose just for you.
ね？
Right?
とある竜の恋の歌
A Certain Dragon's Love Song
音のない大地に
Upon this soundless land
恋の歌 響けば
When a love song resonates
狂い出す歯車
The gears begin to spin madly
止められぬ運命(さだめ)が
An unstoppable destiny
はじけた
Burst open
よみがえる今
Reviving now
いにしえより 聖域(せいき)
The sanctuary from ancient times
爆導(ばくどう)の 恋
The explosive love
目覚めた
Has awakened
絆を求めて
Seeking our bonds
焔(ほむら)は ほとばしる
The flames gush forth
破壊と再生
Destruction and rebirth
気高き 君の 呪縛
Your noble spell
突き通る 魂
The soul that pierces through
嘘もなく 気高く
Nobly, without lies
限界も抱えて
Embracing even our limits
未熟な 恋も 糧(かて)
Even immature love is nourishment
愚かさ つちかい
Cultivating foolishness
今 二人 照らす
Now, shining on us both
つかの間の 時 重ねた
Our brief moments overlapped
絆の行方を
The whereabouts of our bonds
両手で抱きしめた
I embraced with both hands
終わりと始まり
The end and the beginning
尊き 君の 記憶
Your precious memory
絆を求めて
Seeking bonds
言葉を放つ
Casting words
破壊と再生
Destruction and rebirth
気高い君の呪縛
Your noble curse
絆の行方を
The whereabouts of bonds
両手で抱きしめた
I hugged with both hands
終わりと始まり
The end and the beginning
遠い君の記憶
Your distant memory
(どこか懐かしいだれかと出会う度に、頭に浮かぶ映像が鮮明になってくる)
(Every time I meet someone nostalgic, the images that come to mind become clearer)
(もう少しで……何かがわかりそうな気がした)
(I felt like I was close to understanding something...)
それって、ライブなんじゃないかな？
Isn't that... a live performance?
ライブ？
Live?
うん。そう、私、旅芸人だから噂で聞いたことがあるんだけど
Yeah. As a traveling entertainer, I've heard rumors about it.
「オンガク」があった頃には、よく開催されてたんだって
They say they were held often back when 'Music' existed.
(そうだ、あたしはライブをやっていたんだ…)
(That's right, I was doing live performances...)
ねえ、気になるなら今からここで私といっしょにやってみる？
Hey, if you're curious, do you want to try it here with me now?
え？
Eh?
ていうかやろうよ！ あなたとならやってみたい！
I mean, let's do it! I want to try it with you!
「ライブ」ってやつを！
A 'live performance'!
遠くで聞こえる
I hear it from afar
わたしを呼ぶ声
The voice calling me
あなたの涙の
The reason for your tears
理由を知ってたはずなのに
I should have known why
乾く前に
Before they dry
枯れる前に
Before they wither
全て捧げようと
Wishing to offer everything
あなたにだけ
Only to you
なにを求めるのか 誰を愛するのかさえ
What to seek, even whom to love
わからず
Without knowing
灰のように朽ちていく心に
In a heart decaying like ash
あなたのかけらだけは
Only your fragments remain
手探りでも かたちをなぞれば
Even if by touch, if I trace the shape
長い眠りの中
In a long sleep
あなたを 夢見るでしょう
I will probably dream of you
ふたり 見慣れたあの時間を何度でも
The two of us, those familiar times over and over
夜明けは あなたにだけ
The dawn is for you alone
空には もう果てがないから
Because there's no end to the sky anymore
なにを求めたのか 遠い日のわたしに今
What did I seek? To my former self, now
問いかけ
I ask
砕かれ色褪せ落ちていく あの
Broken, faded, falling...
かけらたちはどこへ
Where are those fragments going?
手探りでも
Even if fumbling
かたちをなぞった
I traced the shape
長い夢の中で
In a long dream
いま
Now
あなたと
With you
また出会えた
I met you again
ふたり願った
We both wished for
この瞬間
This moment
最後まで
Until the end
ひろがる
Spreading
青い空が
The blue sky
あなたを
You
いつでも見てるから
Because I'm always watching you
（光の塔はもう目の前に迫っていた）
(The Tower of Light was already looming before my eyes.)
（それにつれて、頭に浮かぶ映像はさらに鮮明になってきていた）
(As I drew closer, the images in my head became even clearer.)
（まるで夢から覚めるように）
(Like waking from a dream.)
（まるでそれが本物であるかのように）
(As if it were the real thing.)
（――「ライブ」をしていた場所が）
(The place where we held... the "live".)
……着いた
I've arrived.
ここが……光の塔
So this is... the Tower of Light.
塔っていうよりも、何かの舞台みたいにも見えるな
Looks more like a stage of some sort than a tower.
似てる……気がする
I feel like... it's similar.
あの、「ライブ」をやっていた場所に
To that place where we held the "live"...
いらっしゃい、ライオンさん
Welcome, Mr. Lion.
キミが……願いを叶えてくれる「天使」？
Are you... the "angel" who grants wishes?
うん、そう。キミが来るのを待ってたよ
Yeah, that's right. I've been waiting for you.
この世界に……「オンガク」を取り戻すことができるキミを
For you, who can bring "music" back to this world.
「オンガク」を？ あたしが……？
Music? Me...?
そうだよ
That's right.
ここに来るまでにたくさんのものを受け取ったキミは、もう「オンガク」が何か分かってるんじゃないかな？
Having received so many things on your way here, I think you already know what "music" is, don't you?
ほら、ボクといっしょに飛ぼう
Come, let's fly together.
震え出した絶望の淵で
At the edge of trembling despair
私を抱きしめてください
Please hold me tight
静寂に埋め尽くされ
Filled with silence
独りで凍えてる
I'm freezing all alone
崩れ落ちてゆく 楽園の果てで
At the edge of a crumbling paradise
忘れられた祈りが響いてる
Forgotten prayers are echoing
支配する闇の中でも
Even in the darkness that dominates
枯れない愛を目覚めよ
Awaken the love that never withers
永遠に
Forever
無限に降る孤独を
The infinite loneliness falling down
その指で染めてください
Please color it with your fingers
叫ぶこの心が
This screaming heart
悲しみを癒せるように
So that it can heal the sadness
まだ見ぬあの光の景色へ
To the scenery of light yet unseen
乱れ咲く花より深く
Deeper than the flowers in full bloom
優しく口づけてください
Please kiss me gently
ためらいの吐息さえも
Even the sighs of hesitation
命の...
Of life...
...灯してく
...keep lighting up.
滲む幻
A blurring phantom,
祝宴の鐘を
The celebratory bells.
その温もり素肌に
Until that warmth reaches
伝うまで
your bare skin.
ほとばしる嵐の中も
Even amidst a surging storm,
止まない
it won't stop.
愛を、目覚めよ
Love, awaken now.
抗えぬ願いを
An unyielding wish—
その身で迎えてください
please welcome it into your heart.
出会えた喜びに
With a bare heart trembling
震えてる裸の心で
with the joy of our meeting,
求めるあの、残酷の彼方へ
towards that beyond of cruelty we seek.
こぼれ散る涙が
When the overflowing tears
キラキラと風に舞う頃
dance sparkling in the wind,
絆よ、痛みを、支え
oh bond, support this pain,
永遠に消えないように
so that it never fades away.
無限に降る孤独を
Please entrust to me
私に預けてください
this infinitely falling loneliness.
呼びあえた心が
Hearts that called out to each other
扉を放ち、羽ばたく
throw open the doors and take flight,
近づくあの、はじまりの空へ
approaching that sky of beginnings.
へー、この街の露店は品揃えがいいな。
Heh, the stalls in this town have a good selection.
他では見ない珍しいものがいっぱいある。
There are lots of rare things I don't see elsewhere.
旅を続けてると、やっぱりどうしても装備品は必要になってくるからな……。
As I continue my journey, equipment inevitably becomes necessary...
ちょっと覗いていこう。
Let's take a peek.
あ、これいいな。「ブランケットインクッション」
Ah, this is nice. "Blanket-in-Cushion."
ブランケットなのに、袋に収納すればクッションにもなるから、これがあればどこでも一休みできて、旅のお供にピッタリかも。
Even though it's a blanket, it becomes a cushion when stored in its bag, so I can rest anywhere. It might be perfect for a traveling companion.
コンパクトなのにふかふかで、寝心地もよさそう。収納袋の絵もいい感じ。
It's compact yet fluffy, and looks comfortable to sleep on. The illustration on the storage bag is also nice.
こっちはなんだろう？
I wonder what this is?
「SSRBミニウォレット」か……買い物をしたり、小物を収納するのに財布は必要品なんだよね。
"SSRB Mini Wallet"... A wallet is a necessity for shopping or storing small items.
小銭もお札も入れられるっていうのも嬉しいな。今使ってるのも古くなってきたし、そろそろ買い替えてもいいかも。
It's great that it can hold both coins and bills. The one I'm using is getting old, so it might be time to replace it.
お、この「ブレスレット」、かっこいい。
Oh, this "Bracelet" is cool.
デザインが馴染みやすいから普段使いしやすそうだし、ライオンの加護もついてるんだー。
The design is easy to blend in, so it seems easy to use daily, and it even has a lion's blessing.
これをつけてたら君もライオンになれるかも……？なんて。
If you wear this, maybe you can become a lion too...? Just kidding.
ふふ、これかわいいな。ヘルメット被ってる。
Hehe, this is cute. It's wearing a helmet.
「SSRBぬいぐるみキーホルダー」……付けてるだけですっごく楽しい気分になれそう。
"SSRB Plushie Keychain"... Just having it attached seems like it'll make me feel really happy.
手のひらサイズのちょうどいい大きさだからバックパックにぶら下げてもいいし、ベルトに付けるのとかもありかな？
It's just the right palm-size, so I could hang it from my backpack, or maybe attach it to a belt?
これも買い候補っと。
This is also a candidate for purchase.
どうしよう、全部欲しい……。
What should I do? I want them all...
どれにするか迷う……。
I'm torn on which one to pick...
え、これを全部まとめたセットもあるんだ？
Eh, there's even a set that has all of them?
しかもそれだと、収納袋の絵を描いてるトマリ先生の描き下ろしのポストカードと直筆サイン、箔押しメッセージが特典でついてくるのか。
And with that, I'd get a newly drawn postcard by Tomari-sensei, who drew the bag illustration, along with an authentic signature and a foil-stamped message as a bonus.
……セットでください。
...Give me the set, please.
……やっとわかった気がする。
...I think I finally understand.
AZKi、ミオ、わため……。
AZKi, Mio, Watame...
ラオーラ、アキロゼ、リオナ……
Raora, Akirose, Liona...
かなた……。そしてこの舞台に向けて声援を送ってくれていたたくさんのみんな。
Kanata... and everyone who sent their cheers to this stage.
みんなから受け取ったたくさんのもの……そこに込められた想い。
Everything I received from everyone... the feelings put into them.
それらが連なって……“オンガク”になる。
They come together and become "music."
新しいあたしが生まれるんだ。
A new me is being born.
うん。君ならそう言ってくれると思った。
Yeah. I thought you'd say that.
そんな君に僕から……僕たちから……最後に、「曲」を送るよ。
To you, from me... from us... we'll send a song at the end.
今日という素敵な日の最後を飾る……新しい獅白ぼたんの誕生を祝う、世界で一つだけの「曲」。
To decorate the end of this wonderful day today... a song to celebrate the birthday of the new Shishiro Botan, the only one in the world.
今の君なら歌えるはず。 “音楽”を取り戻せるはずだから。
The current you should be able to sing it. Because you should be able to reclaim "music."
がおってこ！
作詞・作曲・編曲：かめりあ
Gaotteko!
Lyrics/Composition/Arrangement: Camellia
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
Gaotteko! Gaotteko!
15分早起きした
Woke up 15 minutes early
奇跡的な起床記録
Miraculous record of waking up
珍しい誇らしい朝
Unusually proud morning
誰のせいでしょうか？
Whose fault is it?
きみのがおが聞こえると
When I hear your roar
気がするだけかもしれないけど
It might just be my imagination but
無敵になる気がして
I feel like I'm invincible
走って 走って 走れんだ
Run, run, I can run
Shine on!
どこで迷っちゃっても
Even if I get lost somewhere
Ride on!
合図は遠くの声
The voice of the signal from afar
迎えに行くよ We're Lions!!
I'll go to meet you, We're Lions!!
Shine on!
きみがいる世界が
The world where you are
Ride on!
輝く合言葉
The shining password
がおっていいやつみんなで
Everyone "Gaotte" together
Everybody, say 1-2-3!!
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
ひとりじゃないって魔法をかけたら
Gaotteko! Gaotteko!
When I cast a magic that says "You're not alone"
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
不安にだって一緒に吠えて
Gaotteko! Gaotteko!
Let's howl together even at anxiety
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
笑顔でバフかけちゃうから
Gaotteko! Gaotteko!
I'll give you a buff with a smile
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
ここがそう 私達の最高
Gaotteko! Gaotteko!
This is our best
Rawr rawr!! Yeah!
一日一獅子 Motivation
Daily Shishi Motivation
低めのやる気がおで上昇
The low motivation goes up
Join us my peeps! 百獣で優勝
Join us my peeps! Winner with a hundred beasts
だからがおっていきましょう
So let's keep "Gaotte"-ing
靴ずれした右足が
The shoe-rubbed right foot
今日のやる気を持ってった
Had today's motivation
椅子の角っこ小指も
The corner of the chair or the little finger
ついでにしばいてくれた
Hit them on the way
きみのがおが聞こえると
When I hear your roar
そんな日もちょっとやさしくなる
Even those days become a bit kinder
おすそわけしたくて
Wanting to share the joy
踊って 踊って 踊ったんだ
Dance, dance, I danced
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
ジャンプするなら今しかないし
Gaotteko! Gaotteko!
If you're going to jump, it's now or never
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
高いトコ目指しちゃおうよ Let's go!
Gaotteko! Gaotteko!
Let's aim for the high places, Let's go!
Shine on!
“この一瞬がプレゼント”
"This moment is a present"
Ride on!
なんて真顔じゃ言えない
I can't say it with a straight face
だから吠えちゃうの We're Lions!!
So I'll roar it, We're Lions!!
Shine on!
きみがいる毎日が
Every day where you are
Ride on!
歌う合言葉
The password we sing
がおっていいやつみんなで
Everyone "Gaotte" together
Everybody, say 1-2-3!!
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
小声でもSay ちゃんと聞こえてる
Gaotteko! Gaotteko!
Even in a small voice, Say it, I can hear it clearly
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
じゃあ叫んだら未来に届く!?
Gaotteko! Gaotteko!
Then if we shout, will it reach the future!?
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
みんなでなら446dB
Gaotteko! Gaotteko!
Together it's 446 decibels
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
ここがそう 私達の最高
Gaotteko! Gaotteko!
This is our best
Rawr rawr!! Yeah!
言葉にすると真っ直ぐすぎて
When I put it into words, it's too straight
くすぐったい胸の奥が！
My chest feels ticklish from the inside!
だからがおってこ！ がおってこ！
「ありがとう」のかわりを
So Gaotteko! Gaotteko!
Instead of "Thank you"
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
ここがそう 私達の最高
Gaotteko! Gaotteko!
This is our best
これは……あたしが見てる夢？
Is this... a dream I'm having?
それとも「ライブ」をしてるあたしの方が、夢のあたしが見てる夢……？
Or is it that "Live" I'm doing that's the dream...?
それとも「ライブ」をしてるあたしの方が、今のあたしが見てる夢……？
Or is the me performing the "live" the dream that the current me is seeing...?
胡蝶の夢って知ってる？
Do you know about the "Butterfly Dream"?
君の言う通り、この世界はもしかしたらもう一人の君が見ている夢なのかもしれないし、
Just as you say, this world might be a dream being seen by another version of you,
もしかしたらさっきまで君が見ていた「ライブ」こそが、この世界の君が見ている夢かもしれない。
or maybe the "live" you were seeing just now is the dream that you in this world are seeing.
もしかしたらいつか訪れる未来なのかもしれないし、観測された違う世界線を垣間見てるだけなのかもしれない。
It might be a future that will come someday, or maybe you're just catching a glimpse of a different observed timeline.
世界は不確定なんだよ。
The world is uncertain.
「音楽」は、そんなたくさんの世界を繋ぐ糸みたいなもの。
Music is like a thread that connects all those many worlds.
数えきれないほど存在する可能性の中、それでも「音楽」だけはいつだってそこにあるものなの。
Among the countless possibilities that exist, music is the one thing that is always there.
うちたちが、ぼたんのことを思う気持ちもね。
And so is the way we feel about you, Botan.
わため、どこにいてもぼたんちゃんのこと大好きだよぉ。
Watame loves you so much, no matter where you are!
ぼたん先輩の絵、また描きたいなー！
I want to draw a picture of Botan-senpai again!
ふふ、ししろと同じ時間をのんびり過ごすの、アキロゼはすごく好きかな。
Hehe, Akirose really likes spending time relaxing with Shishiro.
ぼたん先輩、いつかは私と一緒にまた歌ってほしいです！
Botan-senpai, I hope you'll sing with me again someday!
でも、その前に……
But before that...
せーの！
Ready, set!
誕生日おめでとう！
Happy Birthday!
みんな……
Everyone...
……ありがとう。
...Thank you.
みんなの気持ち、送ってくれたお祝いの言葉……確かに受け取ったよ。
Your feelings, the words of celebration you sent... I've certainly received them.
すごく……すごく、うれしい。
I'm so... so happy.
今ならきっと、前だけを見て走っていられる。
Now, I'm sure I can keep running while looking straight ahead.
これからも新しい世界に、まだ見たことのないたくさんの可能性に、挑戦することができる。
From now on, I can continue to challenge new worlds and many possibilities I haven't seen yet.
だってここが……あたしたちの最高だから。
Because this place... is our best.
だから、この先も一緒に行こう！
So, let's keep going together from here on!
次に生まれるのがどんな世界でも！
No matter what kind of world is born next!
――みんなのこと、本当に本当に大好きだよ！
I love you all so, so much!
（次にあたしが生まれるのは、どこなんだろう）
(I wonder where I will be born next.)
（でも、それがどこでも大丈夫）
(But it's okay, no matter where it is.)
（さよならはいわない）
(I won't say goodbye.)
（きっとあたしはこの幸せな物語を胸に、どこまでだって飛べるはずだから）
(Because I'm sure I can fly anywhere with this happy story in my heart.)
（――そこに「音楽」と、みんなからもらった温かくて優しい想いがあれば！）
(--As long as there is "music" and the warm, kind feelings I received from everyone!)
次の世界で、また会おう――！
Let's meet again in the next world!
きみがいる世界で……！
In the world where you are...!
新しい世界に旅立つ？
Depart for a new world?
SHISHIRO BOTAN BIRTHDAY 3D LIVE
MUST RELIVE